This is where I live. I live in Kenya,
هنا حيث أعيش.أعيش في كينيا,
at the south parts of the Nairobi National Park.
في الجهة الجنوبية من منتزه نيروبي الوطني.
Those are my dad's cows at the back,
هذه أبقار أبي خلفي,
and behind the cows,
وخلف هذه الأبقار,
that's the Nairobi National Park.
يقع منتزه نيروبي الوطني.
Nairobi National Park is not fenced in the south widely,
منتزه نيروبي الوطني ليس مسور في الجهة الجنوبية وعلى نطاق واسع,
which means wild animals like zebras
مما يعني أن حيوانات متوحشة كالحمير الوحشية
migrate out of the park freely.
تهاجر إلى خارج المنتزه بشكل حر.
So predators like lions follow them,
حتى الحيوانات المتوحشة كالأسود تلحق بهم,
and this is what they do.
وهذا ما يفعلونه.
They kill our livestock.
يقتلون ماشيتنا.
This is one of the cows which was killed at night,
هذه إحدى الابقار التي قتلت ليلآ,
and I just woke up in the morning and I found it dead,
وعندما إستيقظت في الصباح وجدتها ميتة,
and I felt so bad,
وشعرت بالسوء,
because it was the only bull we had.
لأنه كان الثور الوحيد الذي نملكه.
My community, the Maasai, we believe that
مجتمعي، الماساي، نعتقد
we came from heaven with all our animals and all the land
بأننا قدمنا من الجنة مع حيواناتنا وأراضينا
for herding them, and that's why we value them so much.
من أجل رعيهم ، لذلك نقدرهم بشكل كبير.
So I grew up hating lions so much.
لذا نشأت وأنا أكره الأسود بشكل كبير.
The morans are the warriors
الموران هم المحاربون
who protect our community and the livestock,
الذين يحمون مجتمعنا وماشيتنا,
and they're also upset about this problem.
وهم كذلك مستاؤون من هذه المشكلة.
So they kill the lions.
لذا قتلوا الأسود.
It's one of the six lions which were killed in Nairobi.
هذا واحد من الأسود الستة الذين قتلوا في نيروبي.
And I think this is why the Nairobi National Park lions are few.
وأظن ان هذا هو سبب أن الأسود قليلون في منتزه نيروبي الوطني.
So a boy, from six to nine years old, in my community
لذا ولد، من عمر ٦ الى ٩ سنوات ، في مجتمعي
is responsible for his dad's cows,
مسئول عن أبقار أبيه،
and that's the same thing which happened to me.
وهذا الأمر ينطبق علي.
So I had to find a way of solving this problem.
لذا كان على أن أجد حل لهذه المشكلة.
And the first idea I got was to use fire,
والفكرة الأولى التي خطرت علي هي استعمال النار،
because I thought lions were scared of fire.
لأن إعتقدت أن الأسود تخاف من النار .
But I came to realize that that didn't really help,
لكني استنتجت أن هذا ليس فعال،
because it was even helping the lions
بل كان يساعد الأسود
to see through the cowshed.
على رؤية مافي الحظيرة
So I didn't give up. I continued.
لذا لم أيأس، وواصلت المحاولة.
And a second idea I got was
والفكرة الثانية التي خطرت لي
to use a scarecrow.
لاستخدام الفزاعة.
I was trying to trick the lions
كنت أحاول أن أخدع الأسود
[into thinking] that I was standing near the cowshed.
بأنني واقف قرب الحظيرة.
But lions are very clever. (Laughter)
لكن الأسود ذكية جدا.
They will come the first day and they see the scarecrow, and they go back,
كانوا يأتون في اليوم الأول ويرون الفزاعة ، ويرجعون،
but the second day, they'll come and they say,
لكن في اليوم الثاني ، يأتون ويقولون،
this thing is not moving here, it's always here. (Laughter)
أن هذا الشي لايتحرك، هو دائما في نفس المكان.
So he jumps in and kills the animals.
لذا يقفزون داخل الحظيرة ويقتلون الحيوانات.
So one night, I was walking around the cowshed with a torch,
لذا في ليلة ، كنت أمشي حول الحظيرة ومعي مشعل،
and that day, the lions didn't come.
وفي هذا اليوم، الأسود لم تأتي .
And I discovered that lions are afraid of a moving light.
واكتشفت أن الأسود تخاف النور المتحرك.
So I had an idea.
لذا كانت لدى هذه الفكرة.
Since I was a small boy,
منذ كنت ولد صغير
I used to work in my room for the whole day,
إعتدت أن أعمل في غرفتي طوال اليوم،
and I even took apart my mom's new radio,
وحتى أن أخذت قطع من راديوا أمي الجديد،
and that day she almost killed me,
وذلك اليوم كادت أن تقتلني،
but I learned a lot about electronics. (Laughter)
ولكني تعلمت الكثير عن الألكترونيات. (ضحك)
So I got an old car battery,
لذا حصلت على بطارية سيارة قديمة،
an indicator box. It's a small device found in a motorcycle,
صندوق الإشارة ، وهو جهاز صغير يوجد في الدراجة النارية ،
and it helps motorists when they want to turn right or left. It blinks.
وهو يساعد سائقي الدراجات حيث يومض عندما يريدون الانعطاف لليمين أو لليسار.
And I got a switch where I can switch on the lights, on and off.
وحصلت على مفتاح حيث استطعت أن اجعل النور يومض وينطفئ.
And that's a small torch from a broken flashlight.
و هذا مشعل صغير من مصباح يدوي مكسور
So I set up everything.
واذا أعددت كل شئ.
As you can see, the solar panel charges the battery,
وكما ترون،اللوح الشمسي يشحن البطارية،
and the battery supplies the power
والبطارية تغذي الطاقة
to the small indicator box. I call it a transformer.
للعلبة الاشارة الصغيرة. التي أدعوها المحول.
And the indicator box makes the lights flash.
و صندوق الأشارة يجعل النور يومض.
As you can see, the bulbs face outside,
وكما ترون، المصباح موجه للخارج
because that's where the lions come from.
لانه المكان الذي تاتي منه الأسود.
And that's how it looks to lions when they come at night.
وهذا كيف تبدو للأسود عندما يأتون في الليل.
The lights flash and trick
النور يومض ويخدع
the lions into thinking I was walking around the cowshed,
الأسود يظنونني أمشي حول الحظيرة
but I was sleeping in my bed.
لكني كنت نائما في سريري
(Laughter)
ضحك
(Applause)
تصفيق
Thanks.
شكرا.
So I set it up in my home two years ago,
اذا جهزتها من بيتي قبل سنتين ،
and since then, we have never experienced any problem with lions.
ومنذ ذلك ، لم أخبر أي مشكلة مع الأسود.
And my neighboring homes heard about this idea.
وجيراني سمعوا عن هذه الفكرة.
One of them was this grandmother.
أحدهم كان جدة .
She had a lot of her animals being killed by lions,
وهي كانت لديه الكثير من الحيوانات الذين قتلهم الأسود،
and she asked me if I could put the lights for her.
وهي سالتني إن كنت أقدر أن أضع لها الأضاءة
And I said, "Yes."
وأجبتها بنعم
So I put the lights. You can see at the back, those are the lion lights.
ولذا وضعت الأضاءة ، وكما ترون في الخلف، هذه هي إضاءة الأسود.
Since now, I've set up seven homes around my community,
ومنذ ذلك الوقت ، جهزت ٧ منازل في مجتمعي،
and they're really working.
وقد نفعهم
And my idea is also being used now all over Kenya
وفكرتي أصبحت مستخدمة في كل أنحاء كينيا
for scaring other predators like hyenas, leopards,
من أجل إخافة بقية الحيوانات المفترسة كالضباع والفهود،
and it's also being used
وهي كذلك إستخدمت
to scare elephants away from people's farms.
من أجل إخافة الفيلة لإبعادهم عن مزارع الناس.
Because of this invention, I was lucky to get a scholarship
بسبب الأختراع، كنت محظوظ لحصولي على منحة دراسية
in one of the best schools in Kenya,
في واحد من أفضل المدارس في كينيا ،
Brookhouse International School,
مدرسة بروك هاوس العالمية،
and I'm really excited about this.
و كنت متحمسة بشأن
My new school now is coming in and helping
مدرستي الجديدة التي أتت لتساعدني
by fundraising and creating an awareness.
بجمع التبرعات وخلق الوعي.
I even took my friends back to my community,
حتى أني أخذت أصدقائي لمجتمعي،
and we're installing the lights to the homes
و قمنا بتركيب الأنوار في البيوت
which don't have [any], and I'm teaching them how to put them.
التي لاتملكها ، وعلمتهم كيفية وضعها .
So one year ago, I was just a boy in the savanna grassland
قبل عام ، كنت صبي في أرض السفانا العشبية
herding my father's cows,
أرعى أبقار أبي،
and I used to see planes flying over,
و إعتدت أن أستعرض الخطط،
and I told myself that one day, I'll be there inside.
وأقول يوما ما ، سأحققها .
And here I am today.
وها أنا اليوم هنا
I got a chance to come by plane for my first time for TED.
حصلت على فرصة لأسافر لأول مرة عبرالطائرة لحضور TED.
So my big dream is to become an aircraft engineer and pilot when I grow up.
اذا حلمي الكبير هو أن أصبح مهندس طيران وطيار عندما أكبر.
I used to hate lions, but now because my invention
إعتدت أن أكره الأسود، لكن الأن بسبب إختراعي
is saving my father's cows and the lions,
الذي حفظ أبقار أبي و الأسود،
we are able to stay with the lions without any conflict.
نحن الآن قادرون على البقاء مع الأسود من غير تعارض.
Ashê olên. It means in my language, thank you very much.
Ashê olên وتعني في لغتي: شكرا جزيلاً.
(Applause)
( تصفيق)
Chris Anderson: You have no idea how exciting it is
كريس أندرسون: أنت ليست لديك فكرة قدرالحماس من هذه الفكرة
to hear a story like yours.
عندما تسمع قصة مثل قصتك.
So you got this scholarship.Richard Turere: Yep.
اذا حصلت على المنحة الدراسية.ريتشارد تورير: نعم.
CA: You're working on other electrical inventions.
كريس :أنت تعمل على إختراعات إلكترونية أخرى.
What's the next one on your list?
ماهو الشي القادم من قائمتك؟
RT: My next invention is,
ريتشارد: إختراعي القادم هو،
I want to make an electric fence.CA: Electric fence?
أريد أن أصنع سور مكهرب. كريس: سور مكهرب؟
RT: But I know electric fences are already invented,
ريتشارد: أعلم أن السور المكهرب قد إخترع بالفعل ،
but I want to make mine.
لكن أريد أن أصنع واحد خاص بي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
CA: You already tried it once, right, and you --RT: I tried it before,
كريس: أنت جربت واحد، صحيح، وأنت ....ريتشارد: جربته من قبل،
but I stopped because it gave me a shock. (Laughter)
ولكن توقفت بسبب تعرضي لصعقة (ضحك)
CA: In the trenches. Richard Turere, you are something else.
كريس: في الخنادق . ريتشارد تورير، أنت شي آخر.
We're going to cheer you on every step of the way, my friend.
نحن سنهتف لك في كل خطوة في الطريق ، أصدقائي .
Thank you so much.RT: Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا جزيلاً. ريتشارد: شكرا لكم. ( تصفيق)